Guide to the Dante Gabriel Rossetti Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 April 28; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.30)
  "I shall hope for the pleasure of your visit at the hour you mention - 1/2 past 3 on Wednesday."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 April 30; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.31)
  "In hurry today I forgot to give you the enclosed ticket for viewing the pictures of my friend Mr. Seddon. If you have time, they are well worth a visit, being most interesting both in subject and complete rendering -- quite beyond most things of the kind."
  Seddon, Thomas, 1821-1856; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 May 12; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.32)
  Rossetti apologizes to Heaton for his delayed response. He tells Heaton he will be happy to show his drawings to Arabella Moulton Barrett, if Heaton arranges an appointment. Rossetti admits that he thinks there is "little [art] worth seeing" in London at the present moment, except for the Royal Academy exhibition. Rossetti notes that the Royal Academy has not exhibited Robert Browning's portrait, despite having accepted it. Rossetti recommends pictures from the collection of William Ward, Earl of Dudley, which are on public display at the Egyptian Hall, and works from Giotto in the Crystal Palace which Rossetti proclaims the "finest sacred art [he] ever saw." Rossetti says that he has spoken to William Holman Hunt on Heaton's behalf and that Hunt is happy to show her his most recent work.
  Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910. Finding of the Saviour in the Temple; Barrett, Arabella, -1868; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Dudley, William Ward, Earl of, 1817-1885 -- Art collections; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 May 13; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.34)
  "Tomorrow by all means, for the pleasure of seeing you and Miss [Arabella Moulton] Barrett. I've written to Mr. [William Holman] Hunt, asking him to fix a day and hour, if tomorrow would not do for him -- is not that best?"
  Barrett, Arabella, -1868; Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 May 15; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.36)
  Rossetti tells Heaton that William Holman Hunt has suggested the next day, at 3 o'clock for his meeting with Arabella Moulton Barrett and asks Heaton to tell Hunt if they can make that time, saying if they can't that they should write to Hunt to rearrange the appointment. Rossetti asks Heaton if he could send the drawing she commissioned from him to a Mrs. Marshall, of Eaton Square, who has been ill and would like to see it, assuring Heaton that Marshall shall keep it for one day only. He has already arranged for it to be sent as he assumed Heaton would not object. He mentions that Marshall has a brother in Leeds who Heaton might know. Rossetti provides Heaton with Hunt's address and gives her instructions on how to find Hunt's house, which is difficult to find.
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 May 21; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 12 x 18 cm, folded to 12 x 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.39)
  "With your leave I will keep the drawing till Saturday -- possibly over Saturday, unless you write to me to the contrary, as people are asking me to look at it. I must apologize for all this delay, but needn't trouble you to answer, unless in the negative. I have not received the other drawing from Mr. Ruskin. Still trusting to show you some progress with the St. John drawing before you leave town."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Mary in the house of St. John; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 late May - June?; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.42)
  Rossetti apologizes for the delay in sending Heaton's drawing which he has now sent along with a sketch of Dante. He has sent the Rachel and Leah case as it reached him, with a broken lid. He says he has a case for the Dante which was not made for it bespoke but which was created by Ruskin's frame maker. Rossetti thinks the case may have been sent to Ruskin's address in Oxford. Rossetti says he hopes he will have the St. John sketch ready to show Heaton before she leaves London. He asks if the drawing of Dante will remain in London after Heaton leaves, expressing his desire to have it easily available to him, should he like to make alterations. In a postscript Rossetti says he thinks that the Brownings will be in London by the 1st of July at the very latest.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October 23; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.51)
  "I'm sorry that I have nothing else to show you since your last visit. The drawing of St. John will soon be getting forward, I trust, but there is nothing of it yet fit to see. I believe the Brownings leave for Florence on Saturday, as perhaps you know. If you are at a loss for some one to take charge of my drawing in London (as I think you said it would not go to Leeds with you) I shall be happy to do so." In a postscript: "I deferred answering your note till near the end of the period of your stay, lest I might have something by then."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Mary in the house of St. John; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 November 28?; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 2 folded sheets (4 pages each): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 56.52)
  With envelope. Addressed from 14 Chatham Place. Date from Fredeman.
  Rossetti tells Heaton that the subjects he is working on for inclusion in a new work by Alfred, Lord Tennyson, are The Palace of Art, Sir Galahad, The Lady of Shalott, Mariana in the South and possibly the Vision of Sin. He describes the drawing of the Palace of Art as being inspired by Tennyson's lines about St. Cecily and says it was commissioned as a watercolor. Rossetti says that if he does not find the repetition too unpleasant, he will produce a duplicate of the work for Heaton but only after he has finished his present work. Rossetti urges Heaton to acquire works by Ford Madox Brown, saying that he has only a few small works left. Rossetti describes Madox Brown's Our Lady of Good Children, a chalk drawing from Beauty and the Beast and a drawing of the Virgin Mary. He provides Heaton with Madox Brown's address and assures Heaton that Brown's work will only increase in value now that "the tide of justice is at last beginning to set in toward [Madox Brown]." Rossetti notes that Madox Brown's Christ Washing Peter's Feet received the Liverpool prize. Rossetti goes on to praise Arthur Hughes, expressing his disappointment that neither he, nor Madox Brown, have been included in the Tennyson work. Rossetti thanks Heaton for her enquiry after the health of Elizabeth Siddall, who is currently in Bath. He states that he would like it if Siddall went to a warmer region for the winter. Rossetti hopes that Siddall and Heaton will one day meet as Siddall "could have no kinder or better friend." Rossetti praises Elizabeth Barrett Browning's Aurora Leigh as "almost beyond anything for exhaustless poetic resource" and as possessing the potential to reveal social truths as did Tennyson's Maud. Rossetti expresses his happiness in hearing that Barrett Browning is in better health.
  Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892; Brown, Ford Madox, 1821-1893; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Siddall, Elizabeth; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1861 September 29; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 61.75)
  "I am sorry to hear from my friend Mr. Rose that his presentation is gone, as I feared, and that he will not have another for three years. Thanks for the list of Governors. The only one I can see who seems at all within reach is Mr. Russell Gurney, but Munro is very intimate in the family. Tomorrow is I believe Munro's wedding-day, as you perhaps know -- or supposing not tomorrow it will be very soon. So he must be busy enough, but I will write him a word."
  Munro, Alexander; Gurney, Russell, 1804-1878; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1861 December 24; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 61.103)
  Addressed from 14 Chatham Place, Blkfrs.
  Rossetti apologizes for his delayed response to Heaton's last letter. He wishes Heaton a merry Christmas. Rossetti says that if he had known that his response would be delayed, he would have written to Heaton to say that he was not sure about the price of the St George watercolour until he was further along with it. He admits that he has been unable to work much on the piece due to other commissions ill health of his wife, Elizabeth Siddall, which prevented her from sitting for the work. He promises that the work will be finished soon and gives its price as 65 guineas, a "very low price compared to many things [Rossetti] has done lately." Rossetti says he has offered Heaton this low price as he is anxious to sell the piece, despite a previous, smaller and less accomplished work selling for 55 guineas, some years ago. Rossetti enquires after a picture that has been sold to a Mr. Miller of Liverpool and expresses his surprise that the work (from the Plint estate) had gone to market. Rossetti asks whether Heaton has been in touch with any of their friends, including her sister and brother-in-law. [The remainder of the letter is lacking.]
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Plint, Thomas Edward, 1823-1861; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1861 December 26; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 2 folded sheets (6 pages): autograph letter signed; each sheet 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 61.105)
  Rossetti is saddened by the death of Mrs. Plint and asked how her children will be looked after. He asks Heaton when the children will be able to benefit from the sale of their mother's collection. Rossetti expresses his happiness that his St George was liked by Ruskin but that he would not make the sale of any of his works dependent on Ruskin's approval. Rossetti says he is offering Heaton the St George at a price "certainly below [his] usual scale of late.". Rossetti complains that artists are at present having difficulty in finding markets for their works while "dealers seem able to make profit enough." Rossetti says the St George should be ready in about a week and says he would be happy to show it to Ruskin before sending it to Heaton. Rossetti asks Heaton not to write about it to Ruskin until Ruskin returns from his travels as "his father opens all his letters in his absence, which is hardly what one reckons on when writing to him of one's affairs."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Plint, Ellen, -1861; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 ca. January 13; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 2 folded sheets (8 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 62.7)
  Rossetti apologizes to Heaton for asking her to send her most recent payment to him by P.O. order rather than check at a time when she is unwell and tells her not to organize the order until she is better. Rossetti remarks that "everyone seems to have had these attacks lately" and that "we may see that they need care to be taken at once, as one has heard lately of so many bad cases beginning with colds of this kind." Rossetti says that he will send Heaton the St. George by the time Heaton specifies and explains that he has not made the "out-of-window bit" brighter, claiming it would create an imbalance of light in the work. Rossetti tells Heaton that Ruskin is visiting him on the day of writing the letter and he can "give no particulars as to [Ruskin's] apparent state when I last saw him, because to tell truth his account of himself was discouraging." Rossetti cannot take the photograph of the oil painting requested by Heaton as it "would be sure to prove a distressing failure." Rossetti recommends Edward Burne-Jones's work Cupid and Psyche Sharpening Arrows to Heaton, remarking that she "could not possibly make a more delightful acquisition." Rossetti ends by telling Heaton that Robert Browning had seen Heaton's St George and expressed a desire to tell Heaton herself what he thought of it.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898. Cupid's forge; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 January 20; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 62.11)
  Date from Fredeman.
  Rossetti apologizes for his delay in writing to Heaton. He admits that Ruskin did not view the St George again, as Ruskin was so delayed in arranging a viewing that Rossetti thought it best to send the drawing to Heaton. Rossetti describes the picture of St George saying "his attention is for the moment diverted by the shouts and trumpeting outside and that he is gazing out toward the procession and crowd." Rossetti promises Heaton that if he has any uncomisssioned work he thinks will please her, he will let her know. Rossetti will send Heaton pieces for a charity exhibition but admits that the only two pieces he has are a watercolor portrait of Robert Browning and a pen and ink drawing from Le Morte d'Arthur. He tells Heaton he will send her the works and requests that she return them the day following the exhibition. Rossetti says that there was a good review of his The early Italian poets in the Spectator a few weeks earlier "but it a sort of work that takes time to get up by a competent reviewer, though fools rush in and the best will necessarily be the latest."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 May 28; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 62.35)
  With envelope. Addressed from 59 Lincoln's Inn Fields. With black mourning border. Elizabeth Siddall died on February 11, 1862.
  "I write according to promise to tell you that I have now 2 water colour drawings finished: After The Ninth Hour, which you saw begun, and Bethlehem Gate, for which you saw a design. In case you would like to pay me a visit and see them, I would appoint Friday or Saturday next at 11 pm or an earlier hour if such would suit you."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Bethlehem Gate; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. After the ninth hour; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 June 24; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 62.38)
  With envelope. Addressed from 59 L.I. Fields. With black mourning border.
  Rossetti thanks Heaton for giving him information regarding Ruskin's whereabouts, saying that he "had but a poor account of him" from Ned Jones. Rossetti says he will be happy to receive a visit from Heaton and Mrs. (Emelia?) Gurney and asks Heaton to give him a suitable time for her visit. Rossetti tells Heaton that Robert Browning was very pleased with Bethlehem Gate and says that he intends to revisit the Virgin's face in the work.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Bethlehem Gate; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 July 16; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 62.49)
  With envelope. Addressed from 59 L.I.F. With black mourning border. Date from Fredeman.
  "I shall be very glad to see you tomorrow at 12. I have just received an extremely nice but I am sorry to say not very hopeful letter from Mr. Ruskin."
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 December 6; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 62.80)
  With envelope. Addressed from 16 Cheyne Walk. With black mourning border.
  Rossetti tells Heaton that he has sent St. George and Princess Sabra to Green and so cannot further alter it, saying that he thought it was better with the previous changes. Rossetti admits that he cannot tell Heaton exactly what Mr. Ruskin said of the piece because he can't remember Ruskin's comments except that "the picture pleased him decidedly." Rossetti promises to mention the "matter of the presentation" to his friend Mr. Rose. Rossetti is sorry that he does not have a day to spare on his return from Newcastle, or he would have visited Leeds and Liverpool on his way home. In a postscript, Rossetti says that he has seen Robert Browning and his son, who is "vastly improved and quite robust."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rose, James Anderson, 1819-1890; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 January 25; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.19)
  With envelope. Addressed from 16 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea. With black mourning border.
  Rossetti thanks Heaton for sending a pamphlet by Edmund Bates and expresses his pleasure that Bates enjoys his picture. Rossetti says he is concerned about his St John and is impatient to correct it. He admits that he made a similar mistake with another watercolor through "incautious use of red lead." Rossetti asks Heaton if she could send him the work. Rossetti is happy in his new home and says he would be glad to show Heaton his old one. He has not heard from Ruskin but is much more at ease with him. Rossetti regrets that he has not responded to Mr and Mrs Aldam Heaton and says he sent them his good wishes at the end of the year, and asks Heaton that she also passes them on. In a postscript, Rossetti says when he wrote to Mr. Heaton it was regarding the painting of a portrait of a Mrs. Leathart.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Mary in the house of St. John; Bates, Edmund, approximately 1816-1896; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Leathart, Maria, 1840-1899; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 May 19; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.54)
  Rossetti describes a "Dantesque" subject ( Beata Beatrix ) he thinks might be suitable for Heaton's latest commission. It is Beatrice seated by a sundial showing the hour of nine o'clock. Rossetti says that nine is an important number in relation to Beatrice in the Vita Nuova, with Dante meeting her at nine years old, Beatrice dying at nine o'clock on 9 June 1290 and with Dante describing Beatrice as a "nine" (the perfect number or symbol). The picture's background will be a landscape, introducing scenes from Dante. Rossetti asks if Heaton would like a work on this subject, around the same size as the Joan of Arc.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beata Beatrix; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 May 22; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.58)
  With envelope. Addressed from 16 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea. Date from Fredeman.
  Rossetti tells Heaton he can offer Heaton a picture of Helen (since she is no longer the subject of his commission for Mr. Rose) or Beatrice. Rossetti can begin the work straight away and gives the price for the piece as 120 guineas, 50 to be paid at the commencement of the work, 35 when presented in advance of completion and 35 upon delivery. Rossetti does not doubt that he can complete it before Heaton leaves London, if he can begin work on it immediately. Rossetti says that Jeptha's daughter (as "a mere shadow") is incapable of functioning as the subject of a work "unless [it is] a dramatic one, of various figures including the incident connected with her." Rossetti muses that his treatment of this (or any other subject) should be independent from that of Tennyson's, stating that he "never illustrate[s] modern writers as a rule, though once or twice I have done so with Browning only, from especial love of him. Such mingling of contemporary ideas is like the intermarriage of the same families, sure to lead to degeneracy."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beata Beatrix; Jephthah's daughter, (Biblical figure); Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence